CRISTHIAN I. CASTRO ARIAS

Mobile phone: +573114248799

Colombia







Data Scientist with experience in Python, SQL, data analysis, Machine Learning, Power BI, among other technologies. I have a background in chemical engineering and quality control that has helped me in the analysis and optimization of processes that occur in the data industry. I am a highly adaptable individual who is comfortable in different roles, willing to learn and unlearn. I have a conversational level in English and enjoy teamwork, sharing knowledge, asking for help and offering support when necessary.

EDUCATION

Bootcamp.	Soy Henry. Data Science, analysis and engineering	(2023 – Current)
Post-Bac.	Platzi. Data Science, analysis and engineering	(2022 – Current)
B. Sc.	Universidad del Valle. Ingeniería Química (2010 – 2015) Dissertation: "Morphology of Chars from Coal-Bagasse Mixtures in a Pyrolysis Process"	

EXPERIENCE

Trapiche Lucerna, Florida, Valle del Cauca **Junior Engineer**, Production Area

May 2020 to Jun 2020

- Supervised management indicator in clarification and evaporation areas.
- Elaborated process diagrams of the sugar mill.

Private Tutor, Bogotá Freelancer, Education

Jan 2017 to Sep 2018

• Prepared students in chemistry, mathematics and physics.

Smurfit Kappa, Yumbo, Valle del Cauca

Mar 2015 to Sep 2015

Intern, Technical and Quality Department

- Executed GMP following local and international standards.
- Supervised sampling of final product and water involved in the process.

PROJECTS

Content-Based Movie Recommendation System

Henry Bootcamp, Jun 2023 - Jul 2023

- Data cleaning and processing of a dataset related to the film industry using Python libraries such as Pandas, NumPy and AST.
- Development of a recommendation model through vectorization, Scikit-Learn and algebraic processes such as cosine similarity.
- Deployment of the application with Render.com and an API built with FastApi.

Morphology of chars from coal-bagasse mixtures in pyrolysis

University of Valle, Cali, Colombia, Aug 2014 - Sep 2015

- Grinding sugar cane bagasse and coal to get the samples of the research.
- Crafting disks made from mixtures of epoxy resin and particles of the grinded samples.
- Checking the disks through microscope and collect images of the chars belonging to mixtures of different proportions.
- Analyze the correlation between the shapes of the chars and properties of the samples like calorific value.

PROFESSIONAL TRAINING AND COURSES

Intermidiate Excel and Dashboards, Platzi, 2023

Spark Fundamentals Platzi, 2023

MongoDB Fundamentals, Platzi, 2023

Docker, Platzi, 2023

Professional Python, Platzi, 2022

SQL and MySQL, Platzi, 2022

Database Building with MySQL, SENA, 2022

Exploratory Data Analysis, SENA, 2022

Advanced English, Colombian American Center, 2017

HSEQ Training, Future Builders, 2015

LANGUAGES

Spanish: Native

English: Intermediate Speaker and Writer, Advanced Reading and Listener

French: Beginner

COMPUTER SKILLS

Programming: Python, SQL, NOSQL, Pandas, NumPy, Scikit-Learn, Matplotlib.

Applications: VS Code, Office 365, Anaconda Suite, Hue, MySQL, PostregreSQL, Power

BI, Mongo Compass

Platforms: Windows, Linux